假如这是你的家  停电了  漆黑一片
What if this was your house? power's out. lights are dead.
你的小孩从床上
Your little ones in their bunk bed
走到过道  一路叫喊
down the hall crying out
妈妈  爸爸  快来啊  我好害怕
Mommy! daddy! come quick! i'm scared!
你必须很快赶到他身边
you need to get there, and fast.
我来啦  宝贝  爸爸来啦
coming, honey! Daddy's coming!
你需要一个武器  不过首先
You'll need a weapon. but first
你需要一支手电筒
you'll need a flashlight.
你要怎么办呢
What are you gonna do?
如何找到它  我来告诉你
How are you gonna find it? i'll tell you how.
夜光手电筒
The glow-in-the-dark flashlight!
大家好  我是戴利设计公司的拉里·戴利
That's right, folks! i'm Larry daiey of daiey devices
这期节目中我们将带给您
And we're gonna spend the next paid-programing block
意想不到得精彩
Rocking your world.
我顺便带来一位朋友
And i brought along a friend to do it.
乔治·福尔曼  女士们先生们
George Foreman, ladies and gentlemen. -okay.
太棒了  拉里  超棒的  他是不是超棒啊
Fantastic, Larry, fantastic! isn't he fantastic, america?
但说真的  两年前你是不是
But, seriously, isn't it true that just two years ago
一间破博物馆的夜间警卫啊
You were working as a night guard at some dusty museum?
没错  两届世界
That is true, two-time world
重量级拳王乔治·福尔曼
heavyweight champ George Foreman!
我只是一个拥有手电筒和梦想的普通人
I was just a reguiar joe with a flashlight and a dream.
你是说普通的拉里
You mean a regular Larry.
但你是戴利设计公司的CEO
But what's no joke is you're ceo of daiey devices
发明了如此必不可少的产品
Creator of such indispensable
比如狗狗们最爱的超级大骨头
items as the Super Big Dog Bone!
-你喜欢那个吗  -不会丢失的钥匙圈
- you like that one? - the unlosabie key ring!
噢  对呀  那个小玩意儿
Oh, yeah, that littie chestnut!
还有你最新的发明...
And now your latest breakthrough...
大家跟我一起说
Say it with me, America !
夜光手电筒
The glow-in-the-dark flashlight!
无论您遇到什么家务问题
Whatever the household crisis
这里是戴利设计公司  能帮您吗
this is Daley Devices.Can I help you?
蒂娜  把这个退给斯图尔特
Tina, give this back to Stewart.
毫无可信度
i don't trust his math,okay?
-那家伙有打电话来了  -又打来
- that guy called again. - again?
拉尔  好消息  我们要和沃尔玛签约了
Lar! huge news! we got the wal-mart meeting.
不会吧  什么时候  三天后
- no! when? - yeah. three days.
好吧  我们有很多事要准备
Okay, all right. we got a lot of work to do.
你有没有听到我说
Well, okay, did you just hear me
我说的是鼎鼎大名的沃尔玛
say "wal" and "Mart" together
我知道  它确实很有名气
Yeah! i know, it's huge.
至少你该兴奋一下吧
So just take a second to be happy about it.
没错
All right.
你完全是在取笑我
You're totally making fun of me.
不  别庆祝得太早
No, let's hold off on the victory
等成功了再说  行吗
parade till  we close, oKay?
说得对
You got it.
他们打算什么时候要见面
And when does he want to meet?
星期五早上十点
They want Friday morning, 10:00 a.m.
好的  我要取消
Okay, then, you know what? cancel that pitch
那个电力螺旋桨的展示
For the electric saw thing with the propelier, all right?
- 我要把它作为重中之重  -行
- i just want to focus on this. - okay.
-重中之重  -我女儿的生日派对也取消
- Just this   - My daughter's birthday, canceled!
你先回家吧  我可能会很晚
You can go home. i'm gonna be pretty late, okay.
好的  老板
Okay, boss.
闭馆整修
你好  不好意思  未经许可的那位先生
Hello! excuse me! unauthorized personnel!
这不是我们的飞黄腾达先生吗
If it isn't our very own mr. success story.
您大驾光临有何指教啊
Come for one of your nostaigia tours?
我好几个月没见你了
i haven't seen you for a few months.
是的  我很忙  这里近况怎样
Yeah, i've been busy. what's going on here?
跨越式发展  他们是这么跟我说的
Progress, so they tell me.
看好了  不久的将来
The future. behold
这里展示的将是2.0版的自然历史
Natural history, version 2.0.
欢迎来到自然历史博物馆
Welcome to the Museum of Natural History
在这里你将看到活生生的历史
where history comes to life
请上前提出你的问题
Step up, ask your question.
然后把机会留给下一个男孩或女孩
Then let the next littie boy or girl have their turn.
你在哪儿出生
Okay, where were you born?
就在这  纽约市  第20街
Right here in new york city, on twentieth street.
1858年10月27日
October 27th, the year of our lord 1858.
废话  废话  漫长的历史  可供学习
Blah, blah, blah. history, history. learning, learning.
逐个改变美国的小孩们
Changing america, one child at a time.
太棒了  那么你加入了
That's great. so you're adding
一些新的互动展示
some new interactive exhibits?
不  戴利先生  不是加  而是彻底的替换
No, Mr. Daley, not adding. replacing the old exhibits.
-他们被送去哪里  -丢掉
- where are they going? - away.
我们要丢掉这些废物
We're getting rid of all this junk.
像这些透视画  蜡像
the dioramas,  the waxworks
还有些破旧的动物标本
Even some of the shabbier animais
比如这只猴子
like this scrawne little monkey
你要当心点  他是一只中南美洲卷尾猴
You should be careful. he's a capuchin.
不就是只猴子
It's a monkey.
但是他的物种很稀有  它是卷尾猴
He's a rare breed. he's a capuchin.
不只是一只普通的猴子
He's not just a monkey.
我就叫它猴子  不必这么苛求
"monkey", then. i said "monkey". why be specific?
扔都要扔了
When you're throwing away a monkey
不需要名字
you don't need their name
你是把它丢掉还是移走
Are you throwing him away or are you moving him?
难道你是灵长类垃圾警察吗
What are you, the primate garbage police?
别管他  亲爱的
let it go, baby.
-这是谁的主意  -当然是我的
- whose idea was this? - me, of course.
我是负责人  还有董事会
I'm in charge. me and the board.
主要是董事会的意见
Mainiy the board.
随便啦  你干嘛这么在乎
Anyway, why do you care?
不  只是人们喜欢这些东西
No, it's just that people love this stuff.
人们  戴利先生  都喜新厌旧
People, mr. Daley, love "what's next?"
你应该知道  不然你不会离开
You should know that. you left.
当时我的处境变了  我的事业刚起步
My situation changed. my business took off...
对  你成了成功企业家  那么
Yeah, you became a success. so
如果我是一个夜间警卫
wouid i, if I was a night guard.
它们要去哪
So where are these guys going?
联邦档案馆的仓库
Deep storage. federai archives.
-在哪里  -华盛顿特区
-where's that? -washington, d.c.
史密森尼博物馆
The smithsonian.
一定还有其他办法
There's got to be something that we can do.
已经决定了  它们明早就被运走
It's done! they leave tomorrow morning.
一切都结束了
it's over.
老兄  你好啊  过得愉快吗
Hey, buddy, how you doing? how you doing with all this?
想要玩这个吗
You want what's in here?
我有东西要给你
You think i got something for you?
一条绳子
You think I got a little rope?
你觉得你比我强壮吗
Think you're stronger than me, huh?
你想要的是它吗
Is that all you got, huh?
劳伦斯  见到你真好  小伙子
Lawance! good to see you, lad!
我也是  泰迪
Yeah, you too, Teddy.
布鲁克林的守护者回来了
The guardian of brooklyn has returned!
麦可菲告诉了我这里的近况
Hey, Ahk. look, Mcphee told me what's going on around here.
-我完全搞不清楚状况  -确实
- i had no idea. - indeed.
发生了很多事  劳伦斯  自从
A lot has transpired, Lawance, since
你上次离开  有人会说...
your last visit. One would say that...
-只是...  -蟋蟀...
- Just... - cricket.
鲍西普斯  过来帮我们一把
Hey, bocephus! little help over here!
老伙计  你们好吗
Hey, fellas. how you doing?
看这儿
Well, iookee here.
这不是了不起的警卫吗
If it ain't mr. big-in-the-britches himseif
正回来赶上跟我们道别
Come back just in time to see us off!
是的  杰迪  我听说了  我不
Yeah, Jed, i heard. look, i don't
明白这是怎么一回事
even know how this happened
是的  确实很难理解
Yeah. yeah, real mystery how this happened.
也许谜底就藏在
Maybe the answer's on
你手中那个神奇的嗡嗡叫的小盒子里
that magic buzzing box there in your hand!
你不在这里  大个子
You weren't here, gigantor!
所以才会这样
hat's how it happened!
一点也不奇怪
Ain't no mystery!
事实上  拉里  这里除了你
The fact is, Larry, there's no one
在上班时间
else here to speak on our behalf
没有人替我们说话
During business hours.
没有人
None, none, dum-dum.
伙计们  没事的
Hey, guys! it's okay!
我早上会打电话给董事会
I'll call the board in the morning
行吗  我现在有一定影响力
all right? I got some pull now
我会处理的  我们会没事的
I'll handle this. we're gonna be okay here.
"我们"  你听到了吗  爱做白日梦的强尼
"we"? did you hear that? you hear daydream johnny?
自从你无情地离开这里
There ain't been a "we" ever since you
这里就没有用过 "我们"两个字
put us on the  "pay no mind" Iist.
这真让人寒心啊  小子
And that's a cold place to be, boy.
拉里  木已成舟
Larry, what's done is done.
就连伟大罗马帝国也有结束的一天
Even the glory of rome had to come to an end.
你可不可以不要
Would you please not look dramatically
边讲边眺望远方
off into the middle distance when you say that?
这使我更心寒
It makes me feel worse.
我不知道你在说什么
I don't know what you're talking about.
你到底在看什么  我在这里啊
Where are you looking? where are you looking? i'm over here.
只是一堵墙
Just a bit of wall.
伙计们  也许情况并没有我们想象得那么糟
Look, guys, maybe it won't be so bad.
对  你说得很有道理
Yes, you make a good point.
但我们现在讲的是史密森博物馆
But this is the smithsonian we're talking about here.
德克斯特  你不懂
Dexter, you don't know that.
你没明白我的意思  大个子
You're missing the point, gigantor!
他们准备把我们运走
they're shipping us out!
拉里  我知道你想让我们好受些
Larry, i know you're trying to make us feel better.
我看得出你也很困扰
I can see that you're genuinely slightly bothered
但一切都不同往日
But it's never going to be the same.
我们所有在这的  要全被运走
All of us here, together, in this place.
这里不再是我们的家了  小子
It ain't never gonna be home, boy.
杰迪戴亚  别这样  劳伦斯
Jedediah, please! Lawance
现在大家都很感伤
these are emotional times for all of us
但也是我们如家人般团聚的最后一晚
But it is our last night as a family
我不愿看到有人自怨自哀的样子
And i don't want to see it squandered in seif-pity.
谁愿意最后一次陪我
So who will join me for one final
漫步这个博物馆
stroll through these hallowed halls?
-你想散步吗  -不
- do you want to go for a waik? - no.
我只想一个人待一会
I'm just gonna squander it in seif-pity.
亲爱的  请吧
My dear, shall we?
一路平安  亲爱的
Safe journey, my love.
德克斯特  要帮忙吗
Hey, Dexter, want some help there?
拜托  不要太伤心  好吗
Hey, come on, man. no hard feelings, all right?
会没事的
It's gonna be fine.
天快亮了  劳伦斯
It's almost dawn, Lawance.
是的  你的大箱子在哪里  泰迪
Yeah. so, where's your crate, Teddy?
我不走  劳伦斯
I won't be making this journey, Lawance.
看来我  小暴龙  还有一些招牌展品
It seems myself, rexy, and a few of the signature exhibits
会留下来  只是暂时的
Will be staying here for now.
不带走碑文吗
Without the tablet?
事实上  劳伦斯
In truth, Lawance
那块碑文会和阿卡门法老一起留在这里
Ahkmenrah's tablet will be remaining here with him.
什么
What?
法老碑文不会跟他们一起离开
They're going without the tablet, my friend.
恐怕今晚是他们的最后一夜
I'm afraid this night is their last.
你没有告诉他们
You didn't tell them.
有时候善意的谎言
Sometimes it's more noble to tell a
比痛苦的实话来得好
small lie than deliver a painfuI truth.
-你会没事的吧  -我尽量
- are you gonna be okay? - i shall do my best.
谁知道呢
And who knows?
说不定巨大的改变会带来
Sometimes the greatest change brings
更好的机会
about even greater opportunity.
看看你自己  劳伦斯
Look at you, Lawance.
你离开这里后  创造了更美好的生活
You left this place and created quite a life for yourself.
也许吧
Yeah, i guess so.
不是或许  我的朋友
I should hope you'd do more than guess, my friend.
你是年轻的企业家  世界尽在你的掌握
You're a captain of industry. the world at your fingertips.
你似乎已经拥有你想要的一切
It seems to me you have everything you wanted.
是的  我明白
Yeah, know, i know.
不  你不明白  小伙子
No, you don't. if i may, lad
请允许我给你一点忠告
Allow me to offer you one piece of advice.
幸福的关键  真正的幸福  是...
The key to happiness, to true happiness, is...
请等一下  我要
Hang on one sec. i just gotta...
一笔日本生意
I got this japanese deal.
不  我要关机  很抱歉
No, okay, i'm turning this off. i'm sorry.
幸福的关键是
The key to happiness?
再会  泰迪
I'll see you, Teddy.
所以他们就这么离开了  你无能为力
So they're gone? there's nothing you can do?
我希望我可以  但我尽力了
I wish there was, man. i'm telling you, i tried everything.
我找了麦可菲  我联络了董事会
I talked to Mcphee, i called the board
但他们今早还是被运走了
but they shipped them out this morning.
好多吃的  老爸
This is a lot of food, dad.
对  艾德今晚会过来  我以为告诉过你了
Yeah. ed from work's gonna come by. i thought i told you.
我们要商量一些公事
We just have to go over a couple of littie work things.
所以你今晚要加班
So you're working tonight.
我以前也工作到很晚  记得吗
to work every night，remember?
那时候你拥有全世界最酷的工作
That was when you had the coolest job in the worid.
是的  但"酷"可付不起
Yeah, well, "cool" doesn't pay for
你的吉他神第六代.
your guitar god VI or whatever.
杰迪
Jed?
杰迪  怎么了...  你怎么打的电话
Jed, what are you... how did you dial the phone?
说来话长  那只无耻的小猴子偷走了碑文
Long story! that brazen littie monkey stole the tablet
我们这里全乱套了
And now we're in a world of hurt, boy!
-发生什么事了  -法老王
- what's going on? - Kahmunrah!
-法老王  -阿卡门法老的哥哥  他在这里
- kahmunrah? - Ahkmenrah's big brother! he's here!
相信我  他不是个好人
and trust me, not a friendly!
我重复一篇  他不是好人
I repeat, not a friendly!
是阿提拉[匈奴王]吗  杰迪
Is that Attila, Jed?
杰迪  你还好吗
Jed? are you okay?
你好 杰迪
hey, Jed.
杰迪
Jed?
发生什么事了
What was that about?
我不知道
I don't know.
来吧  我载你过去妈妈那边!
Here, come on. gonna drop you off at your mom's.
-到底怎么了  老爸  -我要去弄个清楚
- what's going on, dad?  - i'm gonna go find out.
老兄  麦可菲说联邦
Okay, buddy, Mcphee said the federal
档案馆在史密森博物馆里
archives are in the Smithsonian.
告诉我怎么走
Where exactly am i going?
问题就在这  老爸  史密森博物馆
That's the thing, dad. the smithsonian
其实是十九个不同的博物馆
is actually 19 different museums.
他们分布在国家广场
They're laid out around the national mall
从国会大厦一直到林肯记念堂
From the capitol to the lincoln memorial.
博物馆里应有尽有
They got everything there.
有很多很酷的收藏
there's actually some really cool stuff
尼基  专心一点  档案被放在哪个博物馆
Nicky, please focus. which museum are the archives in?
不在里面  而是下面  看起来
Not in, under. it looks like it runs
它在整个史密森的地下运作
underneath the entire Smithsonian.
所以如果阿卡门法老的碑文到了那下面
So if ahkmenrah's tablet is down there...
世界上最大的博物馆就要活过来了
The biggest museum in the world is coming alive.
你的计划到底如何  老爸
What is exactiy is your plan here, dad?
-别担心  -你没有计划  对吧
- don't worry about it. - you have no plan, do you?
尼古拉斯  我有一个非常完美的
Now, nicholas, i have a very good
深思熟虑的计划
Highly thought-out plan.
-你没有计划 -对  我没有
- you have no plan. - yes, i have no plan.
我到了再联络你
I'll call you when i'm in.
给你  谢谢
Here you go. thanks.
欢迎来到世界上最大的博物馆
Welcome to the biggest museum in the world.
这像是一趟旅行
I know, right? it's a trip.
看这架悬在天花板上的飞机
How about these planes dangling from
很奇怪吧
the ceilings, pretty wierd
劳驾  能告诉我如何
Hi, excuse me. could you tell me how
去联邦档案馆吗
to get to the Federal Archives
当然  只要成为一个历史文物
Of course. just be a historical document
值得永久珍藏
worthy of storing for all eternity.
我开玩笑的  他不是一件文物
I'm kidding. he's not a document.
很抱歉  先生  档案都在地底下
I'm sorry, sir, the archives are underground
那里是警戒区
and they're a secure area.
真的吗  森严戒备  好的  谢谢
Really? like, totally secure? okay, thank you.
女士们先生们  博物馆
Ladies and gentlemen, the museum
将在一小时后闭馆
will be closing in one hour.
凭证件入内
法老王之门
法老王
Kahmunrah.
你在干嘛
Hey! what are you doing?
-不准触摸  -不  我没打算碰它
- no touching. - no, i wasn't gonna touch it.
你触犯了"I.T.T."  小子
You're moving in with some I.T.T., bro.
-I.T.T.  -意思是"试图触摸"
- I.T.T.? - that's "intent to touch", homey.
不  我没有  游客不准越过...
No, i wasn't. you're not allowed to go over the...
-什么  你想亲它  -很抱歉
- what, are you gonna kiss it? - all right, sorry.
你用手摸了它  我在那看见了
Put your hand on it and touch it. 'cause i stand there
我在这一整天
And i wait all day
就是为了等像你一样的小女孩进来
for a little girl like you to come in
用她们娇贵的涂了指甲油的
And put her precious nail-polished
手指在文物上乱摸
nails all over the exhibits.
抱歉  我以为
Sorry. last time i checked, i thought
我们生活在一个自由的国度
we lived in a free country
-不  你错了  -不是吗
- no, we don't. - no?
这个叫做美国的国家不允许你触摸
It's the united states of don't touch
你面前的东西
that thing right in front of you
我只是想要...  我有权利看看它吧
I just want to... i'm allowed to look at it here, okay?
你摸一下试试
See what happens when you touch it!
所以你是在威胁我啰
So you're threatening me?
你在威胁我  布兰登
You're threatening me, brandon?
-是布伦登  -抱歉
- it's "Brundon". - excuse me?
-是布伦登  -布伦登对吧
- "Brundon"! - "Brundon"?
-布伦登  -布伦登
- "Brundon". - "Brundon".
人们经常会经常忽略你名牌上的u吗
What, did they run out of u's on your nameplate maker?
我不知道  你经常光顾的那家
I don't know, did they run out of jokes
笑话商店  是不是没有库存了
At the interesting-joke store that you shop at?
抱歉  可是名牌上看起来像"Brandon"
Sorry, it iooks like "brandon", but...
我没空跟你啰嗦  反正是"布伦登"
I'm not here to be your speech therapist. it's Brundon...!
-"布伦登"  好的
- "Brundon".okay...
你以前没听过这个名字吗
you never heard of the name before?
"布伦登"  没有
"Brundon"? no.
去查查1984年最流行的宝宝名字
Look up most popular baby names in 1984.
是"布伦登"
"Brundon".
好吧  你在威胁我吗  布伦登
Okay. are you threatening me, Brundon?
我不知道  阿拉丁小公主, 我有吗
I don't know, princess jasmine. am i?
-月光九号  -对
- oh, wow. lunabeam nine-voit. - yeah.
超棒的电器
Wonderful piece of hardware, huh?
-它的牌子就叫月光九号 -很好
- that's their title, lunabeam nine. - great.
我个人比较喜欢LED的手电筒
I prefer the maglite led myself, but that's just me.
-帮我个忙  什么
- do me a huge favor. - what?
双手插进你的口袋
Shove your hands into your pockets
降低姿态
put your attitude way down
还有  对人友善一点
And, also, be nice to people.
好的  我能问你一件事吗
Great. but couid i just ask you one thing?
-恩  -好的  我要确认下
- yeah.  - okay, so just to be clear
我不能这样做  对吧
so, i can't do this, right?
好吧  你这个疯子
okay, that's actually crazy.
你是不是不想活啦
Did you just make a decision to possibly end your life
早死早超生
Earlier than you were expecting?
我要用手电筒打你
I'm gonna hit you with the flashlight.
-你现在在威胁我   -别碰它
- now you are threatening me. okay. - do not touch it!
-别碰我  -别碰它
- don't touch me. - do not touch it!
-别碰它  -别碰我
- do not touch it! - don't touch me!
我会用手电狠揍你一天
I'll touch you with my flashlight all day.
不 手电筒是用来照明的
No, your flashlight is meant to illuminate.
我要租一台露营车
I will literally rent a camper
我会开着它穿越美国
And we will drive across america
把手电筒对准你的胸膛
with my flashlight on your chest.
-别那样做  -不要怎样
- don't do that. - don't do what?
想要再被捅一次试试吗
Want to see what happens when i do it one more time?
-你来呀  -我量你也不敢
- et's see what happens. - watch you do nothing.
我量你什么也不敢
Let's watch you do nothing when i do this.
听我说  布兰登
Seriousiy, brandon...
-布伦登  -布伦登
- Brundon. - Brundon
你不知道自己在跟谁打交道
You do not know who you're dealing with.
你以为你很会当警卫吗
You think you know what it means to be a guard, huh?
相信我  你不懂如何做一个真正的警卫
Trust me, you don't know the meaning of the word.
我见过你根本无法想像的事
I have seen things that you could not imagine.
-比如说  -我不会告诉你
- like what kind of stuff? - i'm not gonna tell you.
你给我放下手电筒...
but you're gonna drop the flashlight...
你说得好像
The way you said it
你经历过很酷的事
It sounded like you were gonna say something cool.
是的  但我不会讲给你听
Yeah, well, you don't get to hear it.
放下手电筒
Drop the flashlight.
我们讲和了
We cool?
你刚刚的动作简直酷毙了
That's actually pretty cool, what you just did.
谢谢
Thank you.
感觉还行吧
No hard feelings?
抱歉
all right? sorry.
应该是我抱歉  都是我的错  我本该
- i'm sorry.  - no, it's my fault. i shouldn't have...
一只碗不响  两只碗叮铛
No. it takes two opposing forces to cause friction, and...
这是你份内的事儿
And you're just doing your job, all right.
放松点
- take it easy, man. - yeah!
这家伙真棒
That guy's great.
-好  我进来了  -太棒了  你在哪儿
- okay, buddy, i'm in. - great. where are you?
城堡的东北角
The northeast corridor of the castle, just off the commons.
-我要你告诉我去档案馆的路  -好的
- i need you to taik me to the archives. - okay.
走廊的尽头向右转
At the end of the hal, turn right
你左边应该会有个楼梯
And there should be a stairwell coming up on your left.
-我看到了  -这里有点像迷宫
- got it. - now, it's kind of a maze down there.
这些地下通道连接
Those underground tunnels connect
不同的建筑物
a bunch of different buildings.
-相当复杂  -我们得快点儿
- it couid get complicated. - we'd better hurry
离太阳落山只有28分钟了
We only got 28 minutes till sundown.
到地下B层后
When you get down to B level
再左转
you want to take another left...
听得到吗
Can you hear...
尼克  你是...
Nick, you're... nick!
ID 布伦登
Id, 布伦登.
-你来晚啦  -是啊
- later, dude. - all right. yeah.
你们在哪里
All right. where are you guys?
艾米丽亚·爱哈特  首位飞跃大西洋的女性
噢  天哪
Oh, my god.
你这小捣乱  我一会儿再收拾你
You littie troublemaker. i'm gonna deal with you later.
不  不  不
No. no! no, no, no!
不  英语  英语  也许
No, english. english, perhaps.
抱歉  你是谁
I'm sorry, who are you?
我是法老王  王中之王
I am kahmunrah, the great king of the great kings
来自古老历史的最深处
And from the darkest depths of ancient history
我已经复活了
I have come back to life!
也许你没听清楚我刚才说的
Perhaps you did not hear what i just said.
我是几世纪前的埃及法老  早就死了
I am a centuries-old egyptian pharaoh. i was dead
但现在我复活了
But now i have come back to life!
是的  我听到了  欢迎归来
Yeah, no. i heard that. i got that. weicome back.
-你是谁  -拉里·戴利  戴利设计公司
- who are you? - Larry Daley. Daley devices?
就在纽约的上城区  说来有趣
It's up in new york. it's funny
我认识你哥哥  阿卡门法老
i know your brother, AhKmenrah.
-是吗  -恩
- do you? - yeah.
他认识我弟弟  最受宠的孩子
He knows baby brother. the favorite son.
-是的  好孩子  -他是不是刚刚
- yeah, good kid. - isn't he just?
我们的父母总是
You know, mother and father always
把最好的东西给他
gave him the best of everything
一切的一切  甚至是王位
And I do mean everything. They even gave him the throne.
本该属于我的王位
The throne which was rightfully mine!
-这点他倒没提过  -我就知道他不会
- He never mentioned that. - I'll just bet he didn't.
现在  法老王的时代来临了
Well, now begins the era of Kahmunrah
我回来了
Because I have come back!
算了  管他的  把碑文给我就行了
Never mind, just hand me the tablet.
-大个子  别给他  -让他滚
-Don't give it to him, giantor! -Keep him away!
安静  里面的  安静
Silence! Silence in there, please!
-别逼我进来  -来啊  我才不怕
-Don't make me come in there! -No! I won't be muzzled!
听着  那块碑文的能量
Look, that tablet is more powerful than
可不是拉里·戴利设计公司的拉里·戴利
You Larry Daley of Daley Devices
用你的小脑瓜能想像到的
Can possible imagine.
让死人复活只是小把戏而已
Bringing things back to iife is just a parlor trick.
我要用它打开冥界的大门
With it, I shall unlock the gate to the underworld
把我的军队从死亡之境带过来
And bring forth my army from the land of the dead.
所以  如果可以的话
So, if it's not too much trouble...
把它  给我
Hand it over.
好吧  给你
Okay, here you go.
明智的决定
Wise decision.
不好意思  我还以为你要的是方块
Yeah, I know. I'm sorry, I thought you want the cube.
方块
The cube?
魔方
The Cube of Rubik.
好吧
All right
魔方是啥
What is this Cube of Rubik, then?
魔方  就是可以
The cube. you know, the one that
把你的敌人变成尘土的那个方块
Turns all who oppose to dust.
就是那个  算了  总之我想
That one? Whatever. I thought...
是我的错  因为...  顺便说一句
It was my bad, 'cause... you know what? By the way
你弟弟不想着瞎搅合的
Your brother didn't want to mess with it, either.
他想和平解决来着
Yeah, he wanted to play it safe, too.
只是你有点...
Just, you sort of struck me
把我当下等人对待  所以...
As a next-level sort of guy, so I was...
我可不是我弟弟  拉里
I am not my brother, L arry.
只要一眨眼的工夫
I will kill you and your friends
就能杀了你和你的朋友们
in the blink of an eye.
现在带我去找魔方
Now take me to this Cube of Rubik.
-到了  -打开它
-Here it is. -open it.
回来  把我的碑文拿回来
Come back here! Come back here with my tablet!
你朋友还在我手上
I still have your friends!
-你来开  -什么
-Take the wheel! -What?
我说了  "你来开"
I said, take the wheel!
我们开始吧  太刺激了  太刺激了
We're in it now! I love it! I love it!
保持直线就行了  其他的我来处理
Just keep her straight, I'll handle the rest.
现在  冲锋
Now, charge!
现在是什么计划
Okay, so what's the plan here?
我们是美国人  我们不订计划  冲就行了
We're Americans! We don't plan, we do!
坐稳了
Now hold on!
看到没  做了再说  屡试不爽
See that? Act first, think later! Works every time!
干得不错
You're in good hands!
美国第七兵团   乔治·A·卡斯特将军
General George A. Custer of the Fighting U.S. 7th Cavalry
为您效劳
At your service.
乔治·A·卡斯特
1876年小大角印地安战役中败战而闻名
我没事  我没事
I'm good, I'm good!
那边在吵什么  帅哥
What's the rumpus, ace?
小姐  让让好吗
Look, Lady, could you get out of the way?
小姐  你叫谁小姐  我叫艾米丽亚
Lady? Who are you calling lady? The name is Amelia.
艾米丽亚·爱哈特  你应该听说过我吧
Amelia Earhart! Perhaps you've heard of me?
对  你是个著名的飞行员
Oh, right. You're a famous pilot or whatever.
飞行员  我是首个飞越大西洋的女性
Pilot? I was the first woman to fiy the Atiantic!
第一位获得飞行十字勋章的女性
First woman to receive the flying cross
第一位风靡全美的女飞行员
First woman to fly across the 48 states in a gyroprop.
所以你是不是可以正眼看看我
Now if you'd wipe that perhaps-permanent
起码也问声好
look of alarm off your kisser
然后好心的告诉我
I was wondering if you might be so
我到底在哪儿
kind as to tell me exactly where I am.
你在博物馆里  或者  准确的说是在馆底下
You're in a museum. Or, actually, under it.
我现在处境很危险
And I'm in kind of a dangerous situation right now
所以你最好别跟着我
So you might not want to be anywhere near me.
-你动作可真快  -你叫什么  小飞侠
-Wow, you're fast. -What's your name, fiyboy?
我叫拉里·戴利
My name is Larry Daley.
好吧  拉里·戴利  听好了
Well, Larry Daley, in case you weren't listening
我可不怕危险
I'm not one to shy away from danger.
飞矛呢  飞矛你也不怕吗
How about spears? Are you one to shy away from spears?
走着瞧吧  总算有点乐子了
Let's ankle, skipper! Now we're gonna have some fun.
98  99  好了
Ninety-eight, ninety-nine, bingo!
像金羊毛一样闪亮
Like a Golden Fleece.
好了  伙计们
All right, troops
你们的敌人抓住我的那一刻
when your enemies captured me
也让他们成为了我的敌人
They made themseives my enemies as well.
真是大错特错啊
Big mistake. Big mistake.
好了  听我说
All right, here's the plan.
数到三的时候  我会大喊  "进攻"
On the third bugle blast, I shall loudly announce, "Attack!"
同时
At which point
我们就全部冲出去
we will all jump out of this box
然后进攻
And attack.
你们怎么看
What do you think?
你 萨卡家...
You, Sacaja...
我不叫那个名字
That is not my name.
-萨卡杰米亚  -不对
- Sacajamea. - No.
-萨卡在盒子里  -不对
-Sack-in-a-box. -No.
-辛格德玛佑  -我知道你是个著名的将军
-Cinco de mayo. -I know you are a famous generai...
没什么了不起的
That's all right, that's all right.
我和你一样  只是个普通人
I'm a person, just like you.
可是  大叫"进攻"不是提醒了敌人
But won't yelling, "Attack!" alert the enemy
我们要进攻了吗
That we are about to attack?
什么
What?
对  有道理
Yeah, I guess so.
你真是个红人啊  戴利先生
You're quite the popular fellow, Mr. Daley.
为什么不干脆逃跑算了
Why don't you just skedaddle?
我不能逃跑  我朋友还被关在下面
I can't skedaddie. My friends are being held down there.
我得去救他们  我得另想办法
I got to go get them. I got to find another way down.
这幅是新的
This is new.
别紧张  我不会伤害你们的
Hey, it's all right. I don't want to hurt you.
我想他们怕的不是你  戴利先生
I don't think it's you they're afraid of, Mr. Daley.
跟你换  谢了
Trade you. Thanks.
退后  都退后
Back off! Just back off!
我会叉死你们
I will fork you!
那你开叉怎么样
How about you, huh?
永远别让男的来干女人的活
Never send a boy to do a woman's job.
我在麦克罗西亚的部落里
I spent two weeks spear-hunting
学习了两周用叉捕猎
with a tribe in Micronesia.
麦克罗西亚人反应可慢多了
The Micronesians had much slower reflexes.
快跑
Come on!
真是出精彩的民间音乐会啊
Well, this is one humdinger of a hootenanny.
借过  对不起  借过
Excuse me. Sorry. Excuse me.
1945年信号居然还满格
Wow, four bars in 1945.
我在研究这些档案
I've been studying these plans to the Archives.
你下楼梯以后...
Looks like once you get down the stairwell...
我离楼梯已经很远了  尼基
Oh, I'm way past the stairwell, Nicky.
-所有人都找到了吗  -算是吧
- So you found everyone? - Sort of.
你用来说话的小东西是什么玩意
What is that flibberty-widget you are talking to?
-她是谁  -艾米丽亚·爱哈特
- Who's that? - It's Ameiia Earhart.
你找到了艾米丽亚·爱哈特
You found Amelia Earhart?
-等等  -老兄  你急什么
- Wait a minute! - Buddy, what's your hurry?
你没听说吗  战争结束了
Didn't you hear? The war's over!
对不起  有人在追我
Sorry. These guys are chasing me.
什么  那是什么  化妆舞会吗
What? What am I looking at, Mardi Gras?
-你从哪来的  -布鲁克林
- What unit are you from? - I'm from Brooklyn.
什么  你说真的  我住佛拉布斯
What? Are you serious? I'm from Flatbush!
听着  伙计们
hey, fellas!
那群人要给我老乡找麻烦
These so-and-so's are trying to rough up my pal here
就因为他是布鲁克林来的
Just 'cause he's from Brookiyn!
-谢谢  -你瞧好吧  上
-Thank you! -You got it!
先生  你忘了你的...
Hey, mister! You forgot your...
这是什么鬼东西
What the heck is this thing?
打扰了  我替你一会吧
Excuse me. Mind if I get in here?
亲够了没有  戴利先生
Any time you're done, Mr. Daley.
-给我打电话  -真是"谢谢"了
- Call me! - Thank you for that.
忘了正事了吧  戴利先生
So you're quite the smooth operator, aren't you, Mr. Daley?
快
Quick!
-还真管用  -接下来干什么
- That actually worked. - What's next?
听着  不是对你有偏见
Look, nothing personal, but I'm kind
但我现在在这惹上点事
of in the middle of something here.
真的不是你能应付的
That's not reaiiy your fight.
就因为我是女的  对吗
It's because I'm a woman, isn't it?
不  只是因为有一个早已作古的法老
No, it's because I've got this ancient
在追杀我
Raised-from-the-deau evil Pharaoh guy
他会杀了我甚至是我身边的人
Who's willing to kiii me and probabiy
来得到这块碑文
Anyone near me to get this tablet
这样他就能一统天下了
So he can rule the world.
还是因为我是女人
So it is because I'm a woman!
-听着 我...  -不  你听着  戴利先生
- Look, I... - No, you look, Mr. Daley!
要不是因为我
If it weren't for me, you'd still be
你这会还困在那单色彩的世界里呢
Lost in that monochromatic mayhem
-困在什么里  -黑白照片  白痴
- Lost in what? - Black and white photo, you boob!
听着  而且听好了  我能帮你
Now listen, and listen good. I can help you.
我想帮助你  不是因为我喜欢你
I want to help you, and not because
起码现在还不喜欢
I like you, which so far I don't
是因为我闻到了冒险的气味
But because I smell adventure
靠  我要进入你
and, damn it, I want in.
好吧  出了什么事可别怪我
Okay. Don't blame me if something happens to you.
我运气就是好
I should be so lucky.
我是法老王  我继承了母亲的神明血统
I am Kahmunrah. I am half God
我是半个上帝
Once removed on my mother's side
是埃及的合法统治者  也是...
Rightful ruler of Egypt, future ruler of...
未来一切的统治者
Well, everything eise.
现在  我损失了一些手下
Now, I have lost some men.
我需要一些新的将领
So, I am in need of some new generals
加入到我征服全球的
To join me in my little plan
小计划中来
Of conquering this world.
就像沙皇伊万[俄国历史上最残暴的沙皇]
Ivan the terribie.
拿破仑·波拿巴
Napoleon Bonaparte.
还有年轻有为的阿尔·卡彭[著名黑帮老大]
And young Al Capone.
是啊 [他就是阿尔·卡彭]
Yeah.
以及历史上那些最不可思议的
Some of the most despicable
最让人望而生畏的将领们
Most feared leaders in all of history.
先生们
Gentlemen
认识你们真是三生有幸
Really, it's just fantastic to meet you all.
我们也很荣幸
And us, too..
我需要的只是你们的忠诚
All I ask is your allegiance
做为回报  我会跟你们分享整个世界
And in return, I offer you the world.
绝不夸张  还有什么问题吗
Literally. Are there any questions?
我有个问题  你为什么要穿着连衣裙
Yeah, I got one. How come you're wearing a dress?
这不是连衣裙  这是长袍
This is not a dress. This is a tunic.
我保证  这是三千年前最时髦的服装
It was the height of fashion 3,000 years ago, I assure you.
还有问题吗
Are there any other questions?
有  这种裙子
Da. This dress you're wearing
我们也得穿这个吗
Do we have to wear one of these, too?
你没听见吗  我刚回答了卡彭先生
Were you not listening? I just told Mr. Capone here
这不是裙子
That this is not a dress.
这是长袍  差别大着呢
It is, in fact, a tunic. Very big difference.
还有问题吗
Are there any other questions?
跟裙子无关的问题
Any questions not about the dress?
也不关长袍...
Tunic?
好了  快天亮了
All right, then. Moonlight is wasting
-时间很短了 -很短
- And the time is short. - Short?
你说"很短"的时候干嘛看着我
Why do you look at me when you say ''short''?
对不起  我不是故意的
Sorry. It slipped out.
好了  要是说到统治世界的话
Da. If we are taiking about world domination
我当然有兴趣
Then of course, I am interested.
不过有的事情我得先声明
But first I want to clarify something
这样大家才好办事嘛
So you know what you are getting.
人们常说  "恐怖的伊万  他是如此恐怖"
People always say, "Ivan the terribie, he's so terribie".
"他令我闻风丧胆"  "他就是厄运的代名词"
"I'm so scared of Ivan". He's bad news".
可事实上  准确的说法应该是
When in fact, the correct transiation is
"伟大的伊万"
"Ivan the awesome".
伟大的伊万
Ivan the awesome?
这个没那么顺口吧
It's not really as catchy, is it?
"恐怖的伊万"  多么朗朗上口
I mean, ”Ivan the terribie“, that really pops.
可我其实并不恐怖啊
But I wasn't terribie. In fact
我是个平易近人的领袖
I was quite an effective leader.
当然当然  现在我要严肃点
Duly noted. Now, I'd like to wrap up the old meet-and-greet
问各位一个问题
By asking you gentlemen a question.
你们跟我干吗
Are you with me?
-当然  好啊  -是的[法语]
- Yeah. Yeah, sure. - Oui.
好的  不过
- Da, but...
那就把拉里·戴利设计公司的
Then bring Larry Daley
拉里·戴利抓来
of Daley Devices
和那块黄金法老碑文给我带回来吧
And the Golden Tablet of Ahkmenrah to me!
我们会把你弄到你朋友那去的  戴利先生
We'll get you back down to your chums, Mr. Daley.
跟着艾米丽亚·爱哈特走  你不会迷路的
You won't get lost following Amelia Earhart.
快  蹲下
Quick, get down.
戴利先生  我很喜欢你这么搂着我
Well, well, Mr. Daley, I quite like the way you're holding me.
不  对不起  我不是想...
No. Sorry, I wasn't trying to...
拜托  别找借口了  戴利先生
Oh, please, stop beating your gums, Mr. Daley.
打从我们第一次见面起
You haven't been able to take your cheaters off my chassis
你的目光就没离开过我的臀部
Since the moment we met.
我一个字都听不懂
I literally didn't understand one word of that.
是我的幻觉还是确实有音乐响起了
Is it just me or is there music in the air?
说你们呢  小天使  安静点
You! Little flying angel things! Quiet!
他们是丘比特  戴利先生  是爱神
They're cupids, Mr. Daley. Gods of love.
爱神们  你们安静点行不行
Great. Gods of love, would you shut up?
拜托  安静点  我们在逃难
Please shut up. We're trying to hide.
怎么还变了个风格
No, don't change the arrangement
不是曲风的问题  是要你们安静
it's not about the arrangement. Quiet!
一起唱
Kick the chorus, y'all!
给我们露一手  夜间警卫
Yo, show me what you got, night guard!
不容易啊
And so, the little tiny man who
猫大爷终于
Could not be a smaller or shorter mouse
逮住小老鼠了
Runs into the ciaws of the giant cat!
你还真是介意身高的问题啊  对吧
You're really hung up on the height, aren't you?
-不  跟身高无关  -你明明就是
- No, it's not about height, see... - Yes, you are.
你刚才说我是"小"老鼠  而你是"大"猫
You're saying I'm a little mouse, you're a giant cat.
-我本来就是大猫  -无意冒犯  只是...
- I am the giant cat. - No offense, I just...
你是拿破仑  你的姓氏很复杂
You're Napoleon. There's a complex named after you.
-可你就是以矮小而闻名的  -话是没错
- You're famous for being little... - And it's true.
你这天真的美国大男孩
Oh, you naive American man-boy.
听着  反正不是你死就是我活  对吧
Look. Neither of us are gonna be jamming anytime soon, right?
所以不用来这套  我不在乎
So it's not like we should... It's not even an issue.
这可不是身高之类的事
It's not about height or something else.
这是个计划  超级完美的计划
It's a plan. It's a brilliant plan.
-原来是个计划  -直接点  皇帝
- So it was a pian. -Snazzy maneuver, Emperor.
多谢了  小姐 [法语]
Merci, mademoiselle..
要是你的男朋友能够乖乖跟我走...
Now, if your boyfriend wouid kindly come with me...
我不是她男朋友
I'm not her boyfriend.
-不是  -不是
- Not her boyfriend. - No.
只是朋友
Just friends?
-对  朋友  -故交
- Yeah, friends. - Acquaintances. Friends.
你们是大学同学吗
Were you guys, like, friends in college
而且现在怕破坏了你们的关系
And just afraid now to both ruin your reiationship
所以不敢告诉别人
By telling the other person
你们两情相悦
You want to be more than friends
想进一步发展
That you like-like each other?
说慢点行吗  对不起  我没听清
One more time? I'm sorry. I didn't catch the...
我说  你们是不是大学同学
Were you guys, like, friends in college
现在怕破坏了你们的关系
And now both afraid to ruin your reiationship
所以不敢告诉别人
By telling the other person that
你们两情相悦
You want to be more than friends
想进一步发展
That you iike-iike each other?
-不是  -不是吗
- No. - No?
我喜欢这种曲折辗转的爱情
I just love the nitty-gritty of relationships.
法国人谈恋爱都这样
All us French do.
是啊  爱情
Yes. Amor.
-听着  -好的
- Now. - Yeah?
-要么走  要么死  -明白
- This way, or you die. - Yes.
-等等  我要跟你们一起走  -不行  与你无关
- Wait, I'm coming with you! - No! Our fight is not with you.
我头发在欧洲某些地方就像通用货币
My hair is currency in certain parts of Europe.
是真的  像黄金或纸币那样的通用货币
It's true. Currency, like gold or paper money.
听着
Listen up, kemosabe.
这家伙连烙饼和苍蝇拍都分不清
This rodeo clown wouldn't know a flapjack from a flyswatter.
现在大个子在外面为我们冒险
Now, gigantor's out there risking his hide for us.
我们起码要给他提供点帮助
The least we can do is give him some help.
大的帮助  但如果我们一直困在这里
Some big help. But we can't very well do
就什么忙帮不上了  不是吗
thatif we're stuck in here, now, can we?
我们得逃出去
We need to escape.
烙饼是啥
What's a flapjack?
就是一种饼干  或者圆饼
It's like a biscuit or a scone.
-要撞一下吗  -好
- Chest bump? - Yeah.
-准备好了吗  -好了
- Ready? - Ready.
-你俩出来干嘛  -屋大维 快走
- Hey! what are you two doing out here? - Octavius, go!
你先跑  我拖住他们
You, make a run for it, I'll hold them off!
我不会扔下你不管的
I will not leave you!
没时间演罗马戏剧了  就现在  快走
Ain't no time for your Roman melodrama! Now, get! Go!
老杰迪戴亚会没事的
Old Jedediah will be fine.
你现在麻烦大了
Now, you're in real trouble.
它们怎么不是真的宝石
Why, these aren't real rubies at all.
都是假货
Ruby slippers indeed.
不过  无论你是谁   阿尔奇·邦克
But, whoever you are, Archie Bunker
你的王位还是很舒适的
You had one comfortable throne.
老大
Hey, boss.
抓到这个人
Caught this one trying to escape
他想从箱子的小洞里逃跑
Through a rust hole in the crate
他还有一个小朋友逃走了
One of his little friends got away.
拜托  他们能造成什么威胁
Oh, please. What damage couid they possibiy do?
他们还没有米粒大
Why,  they're no bigger than a little grain of couscous.
对不对啊  小朋友
Aren't you?
知道吗  你的话让我想起两个词
You know, two words come to mind when I hear you taLk.
"疯子"和"怪胎"
"Delusional" and "weirdo".
再加一个词的话  就是  "白痴"
And if I had to say a third, "goofy". Just goofy.
现在  把老杰迪戴亚放了
Now you let old Jedediah out of here
不然我就要生气了
Or he's gonna get angry.
演得好  杰迪戴亚
Well played, Jedediah!
对不起  可你实在太可爱了
I'm sorry, I can't take you seriously. You're just adorable
即使你是在威胁我  也实在很可爱
Even when you're threatening me. It's hilarious.
是我的错觉吗  还是这些小人儿都这么可爱
Is it just me, or are these guys unbliievably cute?
等等
Now hold it a second, now.
你有权囚禁我
Now, you have a right to keep me
甚至虐待我
As your captive, otorture me, even
但是别说我可爱  我才不可爱
But don't call me cute! I ain't cute!
冷静  我的朋友  保住性命  我会救你的
Steady, my friend! Just stay alive! I will find you!
大个子  不是吧
Gigantor. No!
你好啊  戴利先生  很高兴又见面了啊
Hello, Mr. Daley. Nice to see you again.
要是你不介意的话  我要把那个拿走了
Now, if you don't mind, I shall take that from you.
谢谢
Thank you.
终于  终于到手了  三千年了
Finally. Finailly! After 3,000 years
我那完美的
My evil army of the damned
受了诅咒的邪恶军团
My beautifui, beautifui army
就要被解放了
Shall be unleashed!
恐怕是父王和母后
I'm afraid that mother and father may have
稍微改了下密码
Slightly changed the combination on me.
看来这整个的解放冥界的事
I guess this whole unleashing-the-underworld thing
没成功啊
Isn't really working out for you, huh?
肯定有点郁闷吧
It must be really frustrating
毕竟你等了数千年
'Cause you've waitednow how to begin
才能复活啊
To come back from the dead and everything
结果现在你打不开那东西
And now you can't get it open.
我才不郁闷  要是必要的话  再等几千年也行
Fear not, for I shall wait a thousand more if I must.
那就好  因为几小时后
Good, 'cause in a few hours you'll be
你就会定在这个失败的位置了
Standing here in a frustrated position, frozen
而我则会和朋友们一起走出去  一定会
And I'll walk out of here with my buddies and that'll be that.
所以  晚上就让你闹好了
So, I got all night
真的啊  整晚  不过
Really? All night? Well!
他可过不了整晚了
He doesn't.
把笼子打开
Open that cage.
-你要干什么  -别碰我  别碰我
- What are you doing? - No touching! No touching!
不准推我
Don't you manhandle me!
-看啊  他生气了  -杰迪
- Look, he's having a little tantrum. - Jed?
你别扭啊  别扭
Don't you squirm ! Don't squirm.
只会适得其反的
It'll only be worse for you.
-放了他  -别担心
- Put him down! - Don't be afraid.
我不会伤害你的
I shan't hurt you.
骗你的
I lied.
我觉得他活不过整晚了  戴利先生
I don't think he has all night at all, Mr. Daley.
看样子
From the looks of things, I'd say
我看他活不过一小时了
He has a little over an hour.
让我出去
Take me out of here!
你受过教育  你应该能弄懂这个碑文
You were the guardian! You know all about this tablet
你明显比我们都聪明
You're obviousiy much more clever than the rest of us.
你也许知道  也许不知道密码
You may or may not know the combination
反正我给你一小时
But I am going to give you
去解开密码
Exactly one hour to figure it out.
你不干的话  我就杀了你朋友
If you do not, I shaill kill your friends.
不要妄想逃跑
And please don't think about escaping
我会盯住你的
For I shall be watching you.
听着  我都不知道要从何开始
Look, I don't even know how to begin
去破解这个密码  真的
to decipher this thing, all right? Really.
太遗憾了
What a pity.
你的牛仔小朋友
And your little cowboy friend seemed
看起来是如此的迷人
Like such a charming little fellow.
好了  戴利先生  抓紧时间
Ah, well. Tick-tock, Mr. Daley.
倒计时开始
Your hour has begun.
伙计  你能行的  我知道你行
Hey! You got this, partner. I know you do.
你一定能行的
You got this!
你回来了  还好吗
There you are! Are you all right?
我担心死了  真的担心死了
I've been worried sick! Sick I tell you.
-不  我很好  -伙计我们下一步做什么
- no, i'm fine. - so what's our next move, partner?
不知道  我得翻译这碑文
I don't know. i just got to get this tablet translated.
哦  好极了  又是这个家伙
Oh, great! this guy again.
听着朋友  我们不想惹麻烦
Look, buddy, we don't want any trouble, all right?
看那
Look at that!
我猜他只是只
I guess our sassy cephalopod was just a
不喜欢离开水的鱼
fish who didn't like being out water
他还只是个孩子
He's not such a ballywagger after all.
很高兴你心情不错
Okay. giad you're happy.
来帮个忙
Hello? a little assistance?
-泰迪  -是的
- hey, teddy! perfect! - yes!
也许你能帮助我们
Maybe you could help us.
我很乐意  但是首先
I'd love to help you, but first things first.
我的鼻子痒的让我抓狂了
My nose is so itchy, it's driving me insane.
我不喜欢有求于人  但是你看到了
I hate to ask, but, as you see
我失去了身体的某些部位
i'm missing body parts
-你能不能帮我挠挠  -乐意效劳
- could you please give us a scratch? - yeah, sure.
太棒了  很精准  再上面一点
Oh, yes! that's exquisite. a llttle over there...
-太舒服了  -还要么
- yes! - more?
舒服极了
Oh, yes! yes! oh, that's...
太棒了  美妙极了
Sweet rutabaga pie, that was divine.
西奥多·罗斯福  随时为您效劳
Theodore roosevelt, at your service.
第二十六届美国总统  他是是个骑士
Twenty-sixth president of the united states, rough rider
国家公园以及
Founder of the national parks
一些其他奇迹的缔造者
and a whole about other stuff.''
-我们认识吗  -不  这还有个泰迪
- have we met? - no, there's another teddy.
我们在纽约还有一个你
we have one of you in new york.
真的吗  他长的怎么样
really? what's he like this
和你很像  除了...
He's pretty much the same, except with...
除了什么  说出来  除了有身体
Except what? say it. except with a body?
-是的  他有身体  -天啊  我一生的痛楚
- yes. he has a body. - oh, dash it, the pain!
-还有匹马  -打扰一下
- and a horse. - excuse me!
我们真的很需要有人帮我们翻译碑文
We really need someone to translate
这写了什么
what's written does that mean?
-你懂象形字吗  -当然
- do you read hierogiyphics? - yes, i do, missy.
这很简单
That's a simple one.
鸟  一名男子与矛
Bird. man with spear.
鱼  昆虫  花瓶
sideways fish. beetle. vase.
它意味着什么
Okay, and what does that mean?
粗略的翻译  它意味着
It means, and this is just a rough translation
一个拿长矛的男人把鸟
''a man with a spear trapped a bird
和鱼困在花瓶里
and a sideways fish, in the vase.
还有昆虫
''and there was also a beetle.''
我不觉得是这样
i don't think that's it.
这只是其中的一种翻译
that's just one possible translation.
另一种解释
Another possibie translation is
你能找到所追寻的组合
''you will find the combination you seek
如果你能解答
''if you figure out the secret at
法老坟墓的秘密
the heart of pharaoh tomb.
那是什么意思
okay, and what does that mean?
我不知道  我是斯芬克斯吗
i don't know! what am i?  The Sphinx?
这是什么  那是什么
''what's this? what's that?'' why
为什么不问问你们自己的泰迪
don't you ask your own Teddy
我保证他会用他的
I'm sure he'd iove to get his grabby
手指摸遍它
littie fingers all over that
说不定还会让他的马舔它
Probabiy let his horse lick it, too!
戴利先生  我们应该去塑像长廊
Mr. Daley, we should be going to the sculpture gallery.
我觉得那会有人
I think there's someone there
对此有更好的想法
might have a better a thought on this
我们要找的人应该就在这
The fellow we're looking for is just down here.
-你好  -你好  小姑娘
- bonsir. - hello, young lady.
打扰下  我们能继续前进吗
Hey, excuse me. could we keep moving, please?
当然可以  但是我们
We certainly could, but then we
会错过一个难得的机会
might miss a rare opportunity
我是说  她是个奇迹  戴利先生
I mean, she is a degas, Mr. Daley.
只是我的朋友被困在沙漏里
Okay, it's just i got a littie buddy stuck in an hourgiass
我早上有个紧急会议
I got a pitch meeting at wal-mart in the morning...
-如果我们能...就好了  -他就在这
- it would be great if we could... - he's right here.
我觉得他会对此有看法
I think he'll have a thought on this.
思想者  很抱歉打断你的思路
Mr. thinker, we're sorry to interrupt your contemplation
我们很需要解决一个
But we really need to figure out the secret
法老坟墓的迷
At the heart of pharaoh's tomb.
我在想  在想
I'm thinking. i'm thinking.
在思考
I'm thinking.
-我在思考  -他什么都不会知道
- i'm thinking. - it's not happening with him.
哇
Oh, wow.
你开玩笑  看那里
You've gotta be kidding me. check that out!
朋友  看这里  我很认真的
Buddy! over here! this is serious.
事实上  是人命关天的事
Apparently, it's a matter of llfe and death.
我告诉你什么是生死攸关
I'll tell you what's a matter of llfe and death.
就是那个美人
That beautifui iady over there.
宝贝  看看我得健美身材
Hey, baby! check out the gun show going on over here!
开火
Firepower!
他的确不是爱因斯坦
He's certainiy no Einstein.
-砰砰  -对啊
- biceps! deitoids... - yeah.
-等下  我看到过一些  -一些什么
- wait a minute. i saw a bunch of those. - a bunch of whats?
-小爱因斯坦  -在哪
- littie Einsteins. - where?
在那  在航空馆
Over there, in air space.
我们要去那
I gotta get over there.
怎么
What?
-没什么  -那你为什么盯着我看
- nothing. - okay. then why are you staring at me?
我不想错过任何一个瞬间
I don't wanna miss a moment.
很好  但是我们应该走了  因为我们
All right, good, but we should get going, 'cause we...
-为什么  -你话太多了
- why? - you taik too much, ace.
我不知道为什么这么做戴利先生
I don't know why i did that, Mr. Daley.
我只是觉得我睡了
I just feel as if i've been asleep
很久  突然
for a long time and suddenly
我醒了
I'm awake.
我可以解释...
I can explain that...
但是真的  我可以  我真的可以
But really, i could. i really...
又来  为什么
Again, why?
很好  你们回来了
Great, you're back.
可以了  很好
Okay. yeah. great.
泰坦尼克的主题曲  很好听  但不合适
Love theme from titanic. good, but not really appropriate.
你不愿享受生活  对吗  戴利先生
You don't let yourself enjoy things much, do you, Mr. Daley?
知道吗  你们挑错歌了
Okay, you know what? it's not really the song choice.
你有点不明事理
And by the way, you're a little pitchy.
但我觉得你们太奇妙了  看上去很棒
well, i thought you were amazing, and you look wonderfui.
你们能飞的远点吗
could you just fiy away, please?
冒险继续
And so the adventure continues.
我是怎么跟你们说的  有完没完
What did i tell you? enough!
我觉得我像只飞翔的蝴蝶
You know, i do sort of feel like a floating butterfly.
你比马路上的蜥蜴还疯狂
You are crazier than a road llzard.
法老阁下  他们俩听说
Mr. egypt, these two here heard
我们想征服世界
that we're thinking of the world
他们想加入  我也不知道他们是谁
And they want in. i don't know who they are
不过他们很显然也是这里的展品
But they're on exhibit here, too, apparently.
我都不知道他们是什么
I don't even know what they are.
很抱歉  我们的核心任务都
I'm sorry, but we're all full up
不缺人手了  真的很抱歉
in our axis business today. Sorry
拜托  我很坏的
Come on! but i'm bad! i'm bad!
我可以让你见识一下我有多坏
Hey, i could show you how bad i am !
怕了吧
Fear me!
不好意思  我不相信你
I'm sorry. i'm just not buying it.
你看上去不是很坏
You don't seem very bad. you just
你只是有点喜怒无常
seem sort of vaguely for me
你在干什么  那是什么手势
What are you doing? what is that? what is this?
什么意思  我很迷茫
What does it mean? you've lost me.
是你在呼吸吗  我什么都听不到
Is that you breathing? because i can't hear myself think.
我能提个简单的建议吗  朋友
Can i make one suggestion to you, my friend? just simpllfy.
我们真的有很多事要做
There's just too much going on here.
你很邪恶  你爱喘气
You're evil, you're asthmatic
你是个机器人  还有那个斗篷是干吗的
you're a robot... and what is the cape for?
我们要去剧院吗  我不这么认为
Are we going to the opera? i don't think so.
抱歉  再见
Sorry! goodbye.
他正带着那个碑文逃跑
He's leaving with the tablet!
哪里
Where?
给我望远镜
Give me that.
他不是在解谜  他想逃跑
He's not trying to figure out the... he's trying to escape!
行动  你们把他给我杀掉  把碑文带回来
Go. go! all of you! klli him ! and bring me that tablet.
快去  行动起来
Come on, people! let's go!
没有那块碑文  我们什么都不是
without that tablet, we are nothing.
冲啊
Go!
你觉得自己能逃走吗  拉里·戴利
Thought you could get away, didn't you, larry Daley?
完了  我们是瓮中之鳖
Criminy, we're jimmy-jacked.
瓮中之鳖  真的吗
jimmy-jacked? really?
那是我说话的方式
it's the way i speak.
我知道  但即使是你听起来也很怪
Yeah, i know, but that one sounds made up, even for you.
我们的路被坏人
''oh, no, our path has been blocked by
堵住了  那多无聊
bad people.'' what's the funny dash!
问题是  我们现在
The point is, we're not getting
进不了航空馆了
into the air space right now
你说对了  我们是
you're right. we are
-瓮中之鳖  -瓮中之鳖
- jimmy-jacked. - jimmy-jacked.
这边
Come on.
他们说有个不错的人在领导这个国家
They say a good man rules this union.
我答应杰迪戴亚会带来救兵
I promised jedediah i would bring help
而救兵就是
And help i wll bring.
冲啊
Charge!
距离判断错误
Misjudged the distance.
谁在那
Who's there?
丘比特  保护我
Jupiter, protect me.
保持不动
Remain very still.
他们能察觉任何动静
They can sense movement.
显然他们也能听到我自言自语
Apparently, they can also hear me talking to myseif.
我不是个坚果
I'm not a nut.
不要
No!
这里应该会安全一阵子
We should be okay in here for a while.
你当了多久的古董警卫
So, how long have you guarded antiquities?
什么  不  我其实不在这里工作
What? oh, no, i don't actually work at the...
我看到你穿了这身制服
I just thought with the fancy getup and all...
不  这是我借来的
yea,no, i borrowed this.
我是说 我曾在纽约当过警卫
I mean, i was a guard back in New
但那是很久以前了
York, but that was a while ago.
你为什么离开  你不喜欢吗
So why did you leave? did you not enjoy it?
不  我很喜欢  只是
No, i loved it. i just...
有些事是会转变的  所以...
Things sort of took off in a different direction, so...
-那你现在在做什么  -我现在...
- so what do you do now? - well, i sort of...
我设计东西然后把它们卖掉
well, i sort of design products and sell them.
-你是个发明家  -是的
- you're an inventor! - i am.
我是个发明家  对  我发明东西
I am an inventor, yeah. i invent stuff.
比如太空船
Like the rocket ship?
-不是  -海上飞机
- no. - the sea plane.
-飞船  -不  不是飞行器
- the dirigible? - no, not aircraft.
是些小东西  像是
Sort of like more small-scale stuff, like...
夜光手电筒  那是我的发明
well, the glow-in-the-dark fiashllght, that was mine.
也算是你的新工作  你喜欢吗
So this new job, do you like it?
是的  我很喜欢  它很让人兴奋
Yeah, i like it a lot. it's exciting. it's...
-怎么  -我只是很疑惑
- what? - i'm just confused, is all.
你不觉得兴奋  你为什么还要做
If you're not excited by it, why do you do it?
我很兴奋啊  我刚刚说了
i am excited by it. i just said...
我知道你说了什么  戴利先生
i know what you said, Mr.Daley.
但我看到的却是一个失去胆量的男人
But what i see in front of me is a man who's lost his moxie.
我没有失去我的...
I have not lost my...
我有胆量
I got my moxie.
你知道为什么我成为一个飞行员吗
Do you know why i became a pilot?
-我不知道  -为了乐趣
- i don't, no. - for the fun of it.
不然为什么去做
Why else would anyone do anything?
了不起的盖茨比
Great gatsby!
我讨厌这些鸽子还有他们不停地叫
Blast these pigeons and their incessant cooing!
-不  总统先生  -好了
- no! Mr. president! sir! - all right.
是时候接见了
time to see the visitors
-请别起来  -这是个伟大的国家
- please don't get up! - ...of this great union! i always say
今天的事要今天做完
leave nothing for tomorrow which can be done today.
阁下你不能出去
Sir, if you go out there
你会吓坏外面的很多人
you're gonna freak a lot of people out!
怪物  我告诉你先生  我不是
Freak? i assure you, sir, i am no freak.
-不  我不是说你是个怪物  -到这来  小朋友
- no, i didn't mean you're a freak... - come here, little one.
事实上  你才是让我害怕的怪物  先生
In fact, if anyone is freakish, i'm afraid it's you, sir.
说实话  你真小
The truth is, you are very small.
我是说即使是和一个正常大小的人类比较
And i mean even for a reguiar-sized human.
什么  你说这个干什么
What? why would you even say that?
我必须诚实
I must be honest.
对啊  诚实  抱歉  很好
Right. okay, honest abe. of course. i'm sorry. great.
总统先生  把那个小人放下来
Come, now, Mr. president, put the little man down
然后做回你的宝座上去
And let's sit our fanny back in that throne of yours.
你有一个积极的态度  我会照做的
You have a can-do attitude, and i shall do as you ask.
谢谢
Thank you.
-去吧  -谢谢
- there you go. - thank you.
就是这个积极的精神
It's that very can-do spirit that has
才让我们建立了如此伟大的国家
defined this remarkable nation for us
-有趣的故事  -他们来了
- interesting story. - they're coming.
在格底斯堡的一夜[独立战争主战场]
One night in gettysburg...
总统先生  我们需要你别动那个
Mr. president, we're gonna need you to hold still now.
-什么  -亚伯拉罕  别动
- what? - abraham, freeze!
别动  我...
Freeze? i...
-谢谢你  -不客气
- thank you. - you're welcome.
-走吧  要去航空馆了  -我想说
- come on, let's get to air and space. -if i may
你们真是让人羡慕的一对
you two make an adorable couple.
-不  我们不是...
- oh, no, we're not...
我们不是  我是说  不是
No, we're not a... i mean, we're not a...
我们不是  我是说  我们不是
''we're not a... i mean, we're not a...''
我从不撒谎
I never lie!
事实上  你们很适合在一起
The truth is, you two are adorabie together.
谢谢  晚安
Thank you. good night.
再会  可爱的女士和小小的男人
Farewell, lovely lady and small, little man.
现在让我们找找看你说的爱因斯坦
Now let's see if we can find these einsteins of yours.
人类模型伟大的一步
One giant leap for a mannequin...
这里是航空馆
D.c., this is air space. we are
我们重新开始工作
back online and full occupation.
塔斯克基飞行员
The tuskegee airmen
再次准备起飞[二战时的黑人飞行队]
Are on the march once again.
你能不能停止叙述
Can you stop narrating everything
我们做的每件事  享受这个时刻就好
we're doing? just living in the moment
塔斯克基飞行员正在享受这个瞬间
The tuskegee airmen are living in the moment!
-爱哈特女士  -你好
- miss earhart? - yes.
-我想感谢你  -谢什么机长
- i wanna say thank you. -what for, captain?
很多人不敢想我们可以飞
A lot of people didn't think we could fiy, either.
谢谢你开创了航路
Thanks for clearing the runway, ma'am.
-比赛去巴黎  -来吧
- race you to paris? - you're on!
不不  我们要
No! not now! we gotta...
那只不过是个很快的飞行
it's just a quick jaunt over the pond.
走吧  我们没时间了  走啊
Come on, we gotta go. we don't have time. come on!
抱歉  我热血沸腾
Sorry, it's in the blood.
就是它  戴利先生
There she is, Mr. Daley.
我的老爷车
Old bessie, the old family bus.
我驾驶它飞越大西洋
that gai took me acgreen for llft-off
我觉得爱因斯坦应该在那边
Okay. i think the einsteins are over here, though.
这是控制机关  飞行检查完毕
This is mission control. flight check complete.
-你去哪了  -发射准备
- where'd you go? where'd they go? - you are clear for launch.
点火
Contact!
华盛顿  这里是任务控制台
D.c., this is mission control.
-不不  -系统运行正常  准备起飞
- no, no! no! - all systems go and green for llft-off.
收到  准备起飞
Roger that. we are green for llft-off.
不  现在绝对不是起飞的时候
No, we're definiteiy not green for any kind of llft-off!
我想知道发射还是不发射
i want a ''go, no-go'' for launch.
绝对不行
i say no-go.
起飞
Go!
-起飞  -不行
- go! - no! no go!
最大角度转向
Torquing angles incoming.
降低高度
Tone it down with the torque. torque it down.
减少转弯角度
De-torque. de-torque.
开始点火
Commence ignition sequence.
-收到  -准许发射
- roger that, flight. - we have launch commit.
-千万别发射  -10
- no. no, no, no! - ten
9  8  7
Nine, eight, seven...
-那是我的  -不  我们没有发射许可
- hey, that's mine. - no, we do not have commit.
重复  我们没有被授权发射
Repeat. we are decommissioning the committal of the launch
现在取消所有发射计划
And it is now a negatory launch phase.
我们今天没有航班  没有着陆
we are in a no-flight，no-go-face
总之今天没有任何飞行
that is a day of none flight.
-好吧  -要说晚安了各位
- fine! - and we're gonna say good night.
谢谢  你们做的很好  现在结束了
Thank you. good work. over now.
-抱歉  -真让人失望
- sorry. - damn, that was disappointing.
我会买一杯咖啡
Come on. i'll buy you a cup of coffee.
你好太空猴子
Hey, little space monkey.
你是爱宝  你好吗
You're able. okay, good. how you doing?
很好  放松
Yes, good. at ease. all right.
你是个很有礼貌的家伙
You're a polite little fella, aren't you?
你知道那些
Hey, you happen to know where those
会摇头的小爱因斯坦在哪吗
little einstein bobble head guys are?
戴利先生  我找到爱因斯坦了
Mr. Daley! i found your einsteins.
太棒了
Great. hey...
先生们  我们正在设法破解
Gentiemen, we're trying to crack the
这块碑文上的密码
combination of this tablet
它说我们会找到答案如果我们
And the writing here says we'll find it
破解法老坟墓之谜
If we figure out the secret at the heart of pharaoh's tomb.
那很简单  答案就在问题中
That's an easy one. the answer's in the question.
-什么意思  -解开
- what does that mean? - ''figure out''.
是个数字
It's a figure! i.e., a number.
还有法老坟墓  就是金字塔
And the pharaoh's tomb, i.e. the pyramids.
懂了吗孩子  你要找的密码
Don't you get it, kid? you're looking for the secret number
就在金字塔的中心
At the heart of the pyramids.
那这个答案就是圆周率
well, whistie me dixie, the answer's pi!
-圆周率  -准确地说是3.14159265
- pi? - 3.14159265, to be exact.
对  就是3.1495265
Yes! 3.1495265.
不  是 3.14159265
No, no, no, 3.14159265.
很好  3.14...
Yeah, okay, 3.14...
我看不出来你在说对还是错  你可否
I'm sorry, i can't tell. is it yes or no? cause you just...
我知道很难  你只要...
I know it's hard, could you just...
别朋友我的头发
Don't touch the hair.
抱歉  我看不出是上下还是...
sorry, i can't tell if it's up or...
我是摇头公仔
i'm a bobble head
这就是我们喜欢的方式  大家一起来
And that's the way we like it. all together, now!
这是我们喜欢的方式
That's the way we like it
你们不能都是爱因斯坦  所以...
You know, we can't all be einsteins, so...
-我是  -我们都是
- i can! - we are!
-他是  -我也是
- he is! - me, too!
-好吧  -说吧
- okay, all right. - okay, here it is.
-你能不能说慢点  -好的
- can you siow it down a little bit? - okay.
3.14159265
3.14159265.
-很好  3.14  -我记住了
- okay. 3.14... - i've got it.
-非常感谢  爱因斯坦先生  -谢谢
- thank you, Mr. einsteins. - thank you.
好吧  我这个聪明
All right. now, like the brilliant
又著名的将军站在这儿
and famous general that i am.
根据你刚刚说的
I thought long and hard about what you said
我想出了一个新的改进后的进攻计划
And i've come up with a brand-new and improved battle plan!
我要大声宣布  我们不是
I will loudly announce that we are not
去进攻  然后
Going to attack, and then...
等一等
Wait for it.
神奇的卡斯特还会说什么
''what's the amazing custer about to say
然后
now? i hope he's mmoxie in you yet.
我们进攻
We attack!
你也不希望你的朋友跑得这么快吧
Didn't expect your friend to run off like that, did you?
他会回来的
He's coming back, ka-ka-ro.
当月光照进来  他就会回来了
Sure as moon shines on a mongoose, he'll be here.
如果我是你  我就会省口气
I would save my breath if i were you.
你没有多少时间了
You don't have many left.
我们还有十分钟去救杰迪
We've got about 10 minutes to get over there to jed.
我觉得我们合作得很好  不只是个团队
I think we make a good team, perhaps more than a team.
等一下
Wait. okay, wait.
怎么了  你不喜欢吻我吗
What's the matter? you didn't like kissing me?
不  我喜欢  感觉很棒
No, i did. it was great. i mean
我是说耳光有点疼
the slapping hurt a little bit.
那就是你不喜欢我
so you don't like me, then.
我当然喜欢你  你很棒
of course i like you incredible
你是个很神奇的人  你很...
I think you're an amazing person. you're...
但有些问题
It's just there are certain issues
阻止我们
that would prevent us form...
-我只是  你不是  -我不是什么
- i just... you're not... - i'm not what
戴利先生
Mr. Daley?
你是个...
Okay. you're made of...
是一个...
Made of...
美妙的事物  你很好
Wonderful things. you're made of good, wonderfui things.
快上来
Come on.
先生们  请帮我们争取点时间
Gentiemen, could you buy us some time please?
我们必须这么做
It'll have to do.
不  那是世界上第一架飞机
No! that's the first plane ever made!
它是由轻质木头和纸做的
It's made out of balsa wood and paper.
它是由云杉木和帆布还有
It's made out of spruce and canvas and
很好的古代工艺制成的
good old-fashioned
你不来吗
Are you coming, or what?
-把路让开  -我可不想
- out of our way! - i don't think so.
他们要跑了
They're getting away!
加油戴利先生  事情越来越有趣了
Hang on, Mr. Daley. things are about to get interesting.
一个女飞行员  太荒谬了
A lady pllot! preposterous!
-非常感谢男孩们  -她很棒
- think again, boys! - oh, she's good.
怎么了  出什么事了
What? what?
一条绳子缠住了  我要去解开它
One of the wires is jammed. i'm going to have to loosen it.
-拿着控制杆  -不  我不要...
- here, take the stick! - no! i'm not gonna... no!
我知道你现在很有胆量
I know you've got moxie in you yet.
胆量不能用来开飞机
Moxie doesn't fiy planes! people who
有飞行执照的人有胆量才能开飞机
have pllots' liceost had him fly planes,ok？
-很好  -她是你的了
- okay. - she's all yours.
我不想  我不想要控制杆
I don't want it! i don't want the stick!
别往下看  戴利先生  你在开飞机
Don't look down, Mr. Daley, but you're fiying an airplane!
Able  开门
Able! the doors!
-弄好了  -抓紧
- got it! - pull!
拉起来
Pull up!
就是这样
Yes!
太棒了  艾米丽亚·爱哈特
Godspeed, amella earhart!
太棒了
Godspeed.
你看上去有点紧张  顶好泡面
Look a little nervous there, ramen noodle.
因为对于我来说  这就象个温泉浴
'cause for me, this is like a spa treatment.
磨砂浴可以去除角质  使肌肤充满活力
Sand baths are really rejuvenating for the skin. exfoliates.
放弃了
Giving up yet?
还没有
Not quite yet, no.
事实上  看看我们能不能使时光流逝
In fact, iet's see if we can't make time fly.
这可笑的声音是什么
What is that funny sound?
停
Stop!
请站住  戴利先生
Right there, please, Mr. daley.
好好好
Well. well, well, well!
你清楚应该怎样进来  戴利先生
You certainiy know how to make an entrance, Mr. daley.
是时候招募一些后备人员了
Time to recruit some backup.
看在你朋友的份上
I hope for your iittie friend's sake, here
你也知道密码了
That you aiso figured out the combination.
-把杰迪交出来 -不
- give me jed. - oh, no, no, no.
给我密码  交出碑文
First, give me the combination and hand over that tabiet.
我会给你的
I'ii give you the tabiet and the combination
放了我的朋友  并把他还给我
When you reiease my friends and give him back to me.
我想放的时候自然会放的
I shaii reiease what i want to reiease
在我想放人的时候
the moment i want to release him
很好  我想给的时候自然会给的
Great. and i'ii reiease what i want to reiease
在我想给的时候
At the exact moment that i want to reiease it, okay?
告诉我密码  交出那块碑文
Tell me the combination and give me that tablet right now
否则我就杀了你的朋友
Or I shall kill all of your friends
就从这个头发像鸟窝的牛仔开始
Starting with the iittie shaggy-headed iittie cowman here.
我头发不是鸟窝  让我对付他
I ain't shaggy-headed! gigantor, iet me take this guy!
别着急  我有碑文在手
Don't worry, i got this handied.
你不放了我的朋友
you don't want to give me my friends
你也别指望拿到密码或碑文
Then you're not gonna get your combination or your tabiet.
-好  告诉你  -很好
- all right, i'll tell you what. - good.
他们不称我为不可信的法老王
They didn't caii me kahmunrah the trustworthy for nothing.
听好  他们不称我为不可信的法老王
Here you go. they didn't caii me kahmunrah the trustworthy!
他们称我为喋血法老王
They caiied me kahmunrah the bioodthirsty
顺我者昌
Who kills whoever doesn't give
逆我者亡
kahmunrah exactly what he wants
我现在就要得到  就是现在
In the moment that he wants it, which is right now
我要拿到密码和碑文
When i had also better get the combination and the tablet!
-他们那样叫你  -埃及语更简洁
- that's what they called you? - It was shorter in egyptian.
好  给我这个
Great, i'ii give you the combination
就给你密码
after you give me that
岂有此理  如果你再碰
How dare you? if you touch that again
我就宰了你
I shall kill you right now.
-好吧  -别碰这个
- okay. - do not touch this.
-这是禁区  -好吧  那么...
- this is a no-touching zone! - good. well, then...
天啊  我不相信你
Oh, my god! i can't beiieve you
过界
reached across the line
我甚至不相信
I can't even beiieve it! oh
天啊  我现在就想宰了你
god, i want to kill you right now
假如你不知道这个密码
If you didn't know this combination
你现在就已经是个死人了
you'd be so dead now
-难以置信  -很好
- it would be unbelievabie. - great
但我知道密码
but i do know the combination
你的手不要过界
Don't cross this line with your hand!
岂有此理  再说就宰了你
How dare you! if you speak again, i'm going to kill you.
你明白吗
Do you understand this?
废话少说  天啊  你准备好了
Don't say it! oh, god, i see you getting ready.
天  闭嘴
-oh, my god, don‘t say anything
再说一句就剁了你
I shall murder you if you talk again.
给我碑文  告诉我密码
Now give me that tablet and tell me the combination.
好  等你放了杰迪和我的朋友
Okay. after you give me jed and release my friends.
-三条规矩你都犯了  -什么
- you did all three! - what?
你说话了  你的手也过界了
You spoke and you reached your hand across!
跟你聊这个  我可以说上一整晚
Look. i can talk to you about this aii night, okay?
-这样好吗
-how about this?
我现在不杀你怎样
How about i don't kiii you right now
我很想宰了你
iike i reaiiy really want to
给你五秒钟
And i give you preciseiy five seconds
给我碑文告诉我密码
To give me that tabiet and teii me the combination?
我们已经拿到了密码  π圆周率
We aiready got the combination. it's pi.
-3.14159265  -不
- 3.14159265. - no!
-嘿  -抱歉
- hey. - sorry.
疯狂头发  他唱歌了  就像个金丝雀
So crazy hair here, he sang. oh, did he sing! like a canary.
抱歉  拉里
I'm sorry, larry.
我没揍你  还记得上次的事吗
i am not fighting you! remember what happened iast time?
-够了  -笨蛋
- that's enough. - stupid man.
-你没事吧?  -没事  谢谢
- you okay? - yeah, thanks.
你肯定很不愉快  拉里
Must be a reai bummer for you, larry
付出全部的勇气和努力
Knowing that aii of your valiant and efforts
到头来却一无所得
but in the end for none
肯定无比失望
What a terribie disappointment you must be to yourseif.
听到嗡嗡声吗
Do you hear that humming sound?
知道是什么声音吗
Do you know what that sound is?
修辞学
It's rhetoricai.
结束之声
That is the sound of the end.
很抱歉  杰迪
I'm sorry, jed.
你尽力了  大个子
You did your best, gigantor.
靠  我差点抓住他了
Dadgum it, we almost had him, too.
很抱歉前几年
No, i mean, i'm sorry i wasn't around
我不在博物馆
the iast coupie years from meseum
-也许这一切都不会发生
-maybe none of this wouid have happened.
-你不明白
-you don't get it
我们并不是因为需要帮助才给你打电话的
I didn't call you 'cause we needed your help.
当然  我们有小麻烦
Sure, we were in a littie pickle
但这不是第一次
But it wouldn't have been the first time
我必须努力打拼我的天地
I had to wrestie my way out of a root sack.
不  伙计  我打电话是因为你需要我们
No, partner. i called you 'cause you needed us.
你过去几年
That fancy suit you've been parading
穿的那件可笑的衣服
around in these past couple years
西装笔挺的
That there's a hanging suit.
虽然很有派头  但没有灵魂
All gussied up, but dead inside.
那不是你
That ain't you.
-告诉你另一件事  -恩
- and I'll tell you another thing. - yeah.
今晚还没有结束
This night ain't over yet.
这个小牛仔想打架
This little midnight cowboy's got some fight ieft in him.
第六感告诉我你也是
Something teiis me you do, too. ho, now!
欢迎来到法老王的新天地
Weicome to the new, extended reign of kahmunrah
埃及第五任法老
Fifth king of egypt
这个世界
And now the world!
赫拉斯  我的勇士们  上前
Horus, ra, my warriors, come forth!
送拉里·戴利和他的朋友归西
Send larry daiey and his friends to their doom !
等等
Halt!
伟大的屋大维回来了
The mighty octavius has returned!
我骑在自然界
I ride on the back of nature's
最可怕的生物上
most fearsome creature
我骑着松鼠
i ride The squirrel!
冲啊  我强壮的战马
Forward now, my mighty steed!
哇  放松点
Whoa, giri! easy.
你想光荣的投降
Do you wish to surrender honorabiy?
或是血溅当场
Or must this end with the spiiiing of your biood?
这就是你伟大的营救计划
This? this is your big rescue?
不  这才是
Oh, no. this is!
那是什么东西
What is that thing?
他叫亚伯拉罕·林肯
The name is abraham lincoin.
-先生  你麻烦大了  -攻击
- and you, sir, are in a heap of troubie! - attack it!
恶心的半鸽子鸟人
Disgusting haif-pigeons!
不  不  不  有人吗
No, no, no! Hello?
永别了  笨蛋
Adios, bird brains!
等等  别走  别走
Wait, wait, wait. no, no!
再见  鸟人
Goodbye, strange birdmen.
别回到冥界
Do not return to the underworid!
就是这样  快滚回冥界去吧
Yes, yes, do go back into the underworid!
感谢你们的出现  晚安
Thank you for coming! good night!
不
No, no!
这太糟了
Oh, this is awkward.
好像我任务完成了
It appears my work here is done.
记住孩子  分裂之家不会久存
Just remember, son, a house divided against itseif can’t stand
永别了
Farewell.
-现在该怎么办  -我不是很明白
-what now? -you know, i'm not quite sure.
我觉得我应该看着他死去
I suppose we shouid probabiy start by watching him die.
弄死他
Make him dead!
又怎么了
Now what?
我们不准备攻击
We are not going to attack right
现在
Now!
抓住他们
Get them !
别害怕拉里  我会帮助杰迪戴亚的
Fear not, Larry! i wiii heip jedediah!
你从后面攻击他们
You come at them from behind!
-怎么回事  -我正在隐蔽
- hey, what's going on? -i'm hiding.
隐蔽  你在干什么  我们需要你
Hiding? what are you doing? come on, we need you.
-我是个败将  -不  你不是
- i'm a failure. - no, you're not.
在小比格霍恩战役
Did you foolishly lead 208 americans to their deaths
你有没有蠢到率领208位美国人去送死
At the battie of littie bighorn?
-不  -不  一点也不好
- no. - no? not good. not good at all.
-不好  -当然  我说个好的战役
-that's not good. -sure, i talk a good game
但事实是  我配不上这些勋章
But the truth of the matter is, i don't deserve these stars.
惨烈的失败让我臭名昭著
I will aiways be famous for my biggest failure.
过去的已经过去
The past is the past, okay?
现在  此刻  今晚
Right now, this moment, this night
是你扬名的之际
This is what you're gonna be remembered for.
这是你最后一战
This is your iast stand.
-他们需要一名领袖  -没错
- they need a leader. - yeah, they need a ieader.
你想成为他们的领袖  对吧
Yeah? you want to be their ieader, huh?
-是的  我愿意  -让我们大干一场
- yeah, i do. - let's do this!
-好吗  -好
- all right? - yeah.
出发
Let's go!
不太妙
Not good!
拉里
Larry!
艾比
Hey, abie!
我想帮忙
I want to help!
太棒了
Oh, great.
你是谁  这是我的博物馆
Who are you? this is my museum!
他是我的人  退后
Well. he's my human. back off!
伙计们
Guys! hey, guys!
现在不是吵架的时候
This is not the time to get into this, aii right?
德克斯特  你再清楚不过
Dexter, you know better.
好吧  你再这样  这就是你的下场
Aii right? that's what happens when you do that!
明白吗
You get that.
停  停  停
Stop! just stop! stop!
听着  你们都是骄傲的卷尾猴
Now, iisten. you're both proud capuchin!
你们必须集中一致抗敌
You need to concentrate on slapping the enemy!
团结一致  好吗
Keep it together, all right?
出发  去大干一场
Come on, iet's go! let's do it!
-杰迪戴亚他们需要我们  -我不去
- jedediah! they need us! - i ain't gonna make it!
害怕这是牛仔的最后一舞
Afraid this cowboy's been to his last hoedown.
屋大维  请记住我是桀骜不羁的...
Octavius, remember me as i was, wild, and free, and...
-不需要下遗言  -我还没说完呢
- no need for final words. - i'm not finished yet.
我希望我们的关系
I want to get to the story of our reiationship
由敌人变为朋友
The evoiution from enemy to friends.
-不  -这会让你哭的
- no! - it'll make you cry!
不  因为你会活下去的
No! because you are going to iive!
-开始吧  -拿着剑
-let's go to work. - have a sword.
剑
Sword!
小心
Incoming!
聪明
That smarts.
你扇  你踢  你扇  你踢
You smack, you kick! you smack, you kick!
你们好吗  伙计
How you doing, fellas?
-没事吧  -再好不过了
- are you all right? - never better.
听着  当我给你信号
Listen, when i give you the signai
我希望你可以拿着它
i want you to u can have it.
-你有计划  -我要把屋子一分为二
- i take it you have a plan. - i'm gonna divide the house.
碑文  现在
The tabiet! now!
当然  你可以拥有
Okay, sure, you can have it.
只要告诉我谁是老大  就给你
Just teii me who the boss is and i'ii give it to you.
或者我应该给法老王  他是你的主人 对吗
Or shouid i give it to kahmunrah? he's your master, right?
他不是我的主人
He is not our master!
真的吗  他举止表现的就是
really? 'cause he acts like he is.
算了  告诉我谁是老大  就给你
But fine, just tell me who the boss is and you can have it.
我就是
Hey! that'd be me.
这男的就是一农民  我是
This man is a peasant! i am the
-这里唯一的贵族  -是的
- only one here who is nobleman. - yes, well
真的  他有更多的勋章和更大的帽子
Reaiiy 'cause he's got more medals and a bigger hat, but...
-谢谢  -你可以得很多勋章
- Thank you.  - You might got a lot of medals
你要是再敢用你的小手
But you put one of your little
碰一下你块碑文
child hands on that tablet again?
它将是你的小手套
It'll be the last thing the tiny
碰到的最后一样东西
Littie mitts of you ever touch
你为什么要碰那小东西
Why would you touch little nippy?
我可以搞定
I can handle this, okay?
你什么也搞不定  你连话都说不清  傻瓜
You can handie nothing! you can barely speak, you fool!
小菜一碟
You know what? no problem.
我会把它交给你
i'll give it to you you see that
你这个劲头十足的小矮子
Oh, you're a spunky little fella !
很聪明  戴利先生
Very ciever, mr. daiey, getting
让他们窝里斗
them to fight amo divided can't..
是的  我可不能保证
Yeah. i can't reaiiy take credit.
-是亚伯拉罕  -没错
- it was abraham i. - yes, well
分裂之家不可久存
You know, a house divided can't...
-不会久存  -是的
- doesn't do well. - yes, well
还是先为你自己想想吧
You should have saved yourself when you had the chance
因为亲手杀了你
Because now i shall have the tremendous pieasure
是件极大乐事
Of killing you myseif!
你是谁
What are you?
我是夜间警卫
I'm the night guard.
不
No!
胜利属于我们
Victory is ours!
没错
Yeah!
我说的正是这样
That's what i'm talking about!
没错
Yeah!
我觉得有人找回了自己的胆量
I'd say somebody found his moxie.
史密森尼之战
The battle of the smithsonian.
也许是不为世人所知  最伟大的战役
Perhaps the greatest battie the worid wiii never know.
我们知道
We'll know.
对
Yeah.
天  还有一个小时天就亮了
Oh, man, i got an hour tiii sunrise.
我得让送杰迪回去
i got to get Jed's back
巨人  为防止你忘记
In case you forgot, gigantor
他们不再要我们了
they don't want us there anymore
但我要
Weii, i do.
可以载我们一程吗
Hey, think you could hook us up with a ride?
当然  荣幸之至
My pieasure, of course.
等一下  还有一件事要办
Hang on a second. one iast thing i got to take care of.
来啊
Come on, boy! come on, come on!
来这里
Get in there!
感觉不错
Feeis good, right?
不客气  天亮后就回水里去
You're welcome! just get back inside by sunrise, okay?
充满希望的时刻
These are promising days, indeed.
好吧  快点  伙计们
All right. hey, come on, guys.
记住  和你弟兄呆在一起
Remember, stay with your buddy, aii right?
好
Good, good.
你回到属于你的一片天
Weii, you're back where you belong.
没错
Yeah. think so.
我该走了
I guess i shouid be going.
艾米丽亚
Hey, ameila.
之前想跟你说
That thing that i was trying to teii you about eariier...
真是很难说
There's not reaiiy an easy way to put this
但早上...
But, in the morning...
我知道将会发生什么  戴利先生
I know what's coming, mr. daiey.
我早就知道
I've always known.
但不要紧
But it doesn't matter.
今晚你给了我千载难逢的奇遇
You've given me the adventure of a iifetime in one night.
我有预感日出会很漂亮
And i have a feeiing it's going to be a beautifui sunrise.
玩得开心点
Have fun.
谢谢
Thanks.
我不了解你  但
I don't know about you feiias, but this
这个老牛仔有了第二个基地
oid cowboy just got the second baset
-她走了  -头也不回...
- there she goes. - straight towards...
加拿大
Canada.
她朝加拿大飞了
She's heading to canada.
她现在航线正确了
No, now she course-corrected.
到楼下来
Here, head on downstairs, guys.
-好吧  -晚安  拉里
-aii righty. -good night, larry.
老兄  进展怎么样了
Hey, boy, how's it going?
劳伦斯  上帝保佑你带他们回来
Lawrence! bless you for bringing them back.
我该说  干得漂亮极了
And might i say, a hearty weii-done is in order.
我该指出
And may i aiso point out
他们不能永远藏在地下室
they cannot hide in the basement forever
没错  我明白了
Yeah. no, i think i got that figured out.
-真的  -是的
- really? - yeah.
太阳出来了
Sun come, dum-dum.
我们的朋友是对的  黎明很快就来了
Our moai friend is right. the dawn will soon be upon us.
泰迪
Hey, teddy.
还记得你说过
Remember the other night you were saying something
幸福的秘诀
About the key to happiness?
-我有吗  -你说  "幸福的秘诀是..."
-did i? -you said, "the key to happiness is..."
然后太阳就升起了  你又变成雕塑
And then the sun came up and you froze.
-我想我明白了  -是吗
-i think i got it figured out. -yes?
和爱你的人一起做喜欢的事
It's doing what you iove, isn't it? with peopie you love.
其实我原想说的是"体力活动"
Actuaiiy, I was going to say ''physicai exercise''
不过做喜欢的事也不错
But the iove thing's good, too.
-劳伦斯  -恩
- lawrence!  - yeah.
欢迎回家  孩子
Weicome home, son.
谢谢
Thanks.
各位  等待已经结束
Weii, foiks, the wait is over.
经过两个月的改建
after two months' renovation
今晚  博物馆的自然历史
Tonight, the museum of naturai history
再次向公众开放
reopens its door to the publlic
你可以看到  纽约人像潮水一样涌入
As you can see, new yorkers are fiooding in
期待看到博物馆发生的变化
Eager to see just what changes are in store.
新的漫漫长夜
With its new, extended night hours
我们得知博物馆将会更有生机
We're toid the museum wiii be more iiveiy than ever.
好了  好了
well, well, well, well!
虽历经漫长岁月  但这制服还是很合身
I see the uniform stiii fits after these long, long years.
是的  也不是那么漫长  但
Yeah, yeah. reaiiy hasn't been that iong, but...
怎样让"胜利"再次回归
So, to what do we owe this ''triumphant'' return?
不是从"公司"中减去  被炒了
Not cut out for the ''corporate'' jungle after all get fired
不  事实上我卖了我公司
No, actuaiiy, i sold my company.
世事真是很奇妙
The worid doth move in mysterious ways.
总有一天  我们除去所有旧物
One day, we've got to get rid of everything old
其次  有钱的无名氏捐赠大笔钱财
The next, a rich, anonymous donor gives a huge endowment.
万物皆不变
Everything stays the same. so...
-不是完全不变  -不
-weii, not exactiy the same, obviousiy. -no.
女士们先生们  名字是西奥多·罗斯福
Buiiy, iads and iadies, the name is theodore roosevelt
自然学家  骑士 第26任美国总统
Naturalist, rough rider and twenty-sixth president of these great United States
来啊  伙计  打猎要徒步的  劳伦斯
Come aiong, lad. the hunt is afoot. lawrence.
嘿  你们要给我口香糖吗?
Hey, you dum-dums bring me gum-gum?
我父母3000年前给我碑文
My parents gave me this tabiet some 3,000 years ago
信任我  给我这无价之宝
Entrusting me with one of my peopie's most pride possession
-它有什么威力  -有什么威力
- does it do anything? - do anything?
如果它什么威力都没有  那就不稀奇了
Yeah. what's the point if it doesn't do anything?
告诉他们
Tell 'em
事实是  它有神奇的力量
Actually, it has a magical power that
可以使这些展品活过来
brings all the exhibit to live
真的  它是怎么做到的
No, really, what's it do?
没什么  它只是装饰而已
Nothing. it's just for decoration.
我就知道
I knew it.
这地方逊毙了  它看起来好假
This piace is lame. this thing doesn't even iook reai.
真的  伙计  这些电子模拟系统真差劲
Seriousiy, dude, these animatronics suck.
-猛犸象  -是的
- mammoth?  - yeah.
绝种了
Extinct!
现在的科技太发达了
today's technology is beyond me.
我知道  它看起来太像真的了
I know. it's so iifeiike.
-没错  -有其他事
- yeah, yeah, yeah. - something else.
这次你会干的更久吧
You'ii stick around a bit ionger this time
有更好的工作  你就再次离开吗
Or you gonna run away again when you get something better?
-我会留下  -在这工作很久
- i'm gonna stay. - stay, for a long time.
-是的  -是的
- yeah. - yeah.
很好  因为夜间警卫走了  你是...
Good. 'cause, as night guards go, you're...
-什么  -最好的
- what? - the best.
你说什么
Excuse me.
说你呢  小孩 不要抱展品
You, the toddler! don't hug the dispiays.
很抱歉
I'm sorry. hi.
我不是想盯着你看  只是
I don't mean to stare. i just...
你看起来很像我认识的一个人
You iook a iot like somebody i know, and...
很多人都这么说
I get that a lot.
-是吗  -我想我长了张大众脸
- do you? - yeah. i guess i have that kind of face.
-很熟悉  -是的
-familiar. -yeah.
你和艾米丽亚·爱哈特是亲戚吗
You're not by any chance reiated to ameiia earhart, are you?
-不是  -不是
- no. - no.
-我不这样认为  -当然你不是
- no, i don't think so. - of course you're not.
-我意思是我不知道  也许
- i mean, i don't know. maybe i'm...
我只是想问问
I just had to ask
她就是飞越太平洋的那个女人
She was that woman who fiew across the pacific.
-大西洋  -大西洋  当然了
- the atiantic. - atiantic. of course.
第一个飞越大西洋的女性
First woman to fiy across the atiantic
她是第一个完成飞行课程的女性
and she received the fly course. First woman to do that.
-太酷了  -是的  她很酷
- that's very cool. - yeah, she was cool.
你应该查查
Hey, you know what you should check
另一个小历史
out is the the half mini truth
你能带我去哪里吗  我总是迷路
Couid you take me there? i'm aiways getting lost.
好的  当然  我带你去
Yeah, i know. sure. yeah, i'ii show you. come on.
谢谢
Thank you.
-我叫拉里·戴利  -苔丝
-i'm larry daley. -tess.
-约瑟夫  吃饭了  -等一下  妈妈
-joseph, time for dinner! -one second, ma!
乔伊·摩托罗拉  马上下来吃饭
Joey motorola, you get down here for supper right now!
我说了等一下  妈妈
I said one second, ma !
我觉得我马上要有大发明了
I really think i'm on to something here